A Guide to the Dean Rusk Papers FA056
Rockefeller Archive Center
Dean Rusk papers
1950-1969, bulk 1952-1960
1952-1960
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rusk, Dean (1909-1994)
Rockefeller Foundation
FA056
2.73 Cubic Feet
Arrangement note
The collection is organized in four series:
Series 1 - Subject Files
Series 2 - Published Articles
Series 3 - Speeches
Series 1066 - Photographs
Biographical/Historical note
David Dean Rusk was born on February 9, 1909, in Cherokee County, Georgia, the fourth of five children of Robert Hugh Rusk and Francis Clotfelter Rusk. In 1931 he graduated from Davidson College. In 1934, as a Rhodes Scholar at St. John's College at Oxford University, Mr. Rusk earned a master's degree in politics, economics, and philosophy.
Mr. Rusk then worked at Mills College in Oakland, California, from 1934 to 1940, teaching government and international relations and serving as dean of faculty while also studying law at the University of California at Berkeley. During the Second World War Mr. Rusk, an Army Reserve officer, served on active duty from 1940 until 1946, rising to the rank of colonel.
Mr. Rusk joined the State Department in 1946 as assistant chief of the division of international security affairs and was later appointed Special Assistant to the Secretary of War. From 1947 to 1949, he was head of the State Department's United Nations desk. From 1949 to 1951, in succession, Mr. Rusk became an Assistant Secretary of State, a Deputy Under Secretary of State, and Assistant Secretary for Far Eastern Affairs.
In March 1952 Mr. Rusk left the State Department to succeed Chester I. Barnard as president of The Rockefeller Foundation. During his eight years with the Foundation, Mr. Rusk oversaw the distribution of about $250,000,000 for various projects, including aid to underdeveloped nations in Asia, Africa, and Latin America. Mr. Rusk also gave numerous speeches to various organizations and institutions and published several articles on U. S. foreign policy, diplomacy, and the role of philanthropy in American society.
On December 12, 1960, President-elect John F. Kennedy designated Mr. Rusk to be Secretary of State. On January 21, 1961, Mr. Rusk was sworn in to head the State Department. He served in the Kennedy and Johnson administrations until 1969. In 1970 Mr. Rusk returned to Georgia and taught international law at the University of Georgia at Athens until his retirement in 1984.
Mr. Rusk married Virginia Foisie in 1937. They had three children, David, Richard, and Peggy Smith.
Mr. Rusk died December 20, 1994, at his home in Athens, Georgia.
Scope and Contents note
The Dean Rusk Papers document the non-official professional activities of Dean Rusk (1909-1994), carried out during his tenure as president of the Rockefeller Foundation from 1952 to 1961. There are no personal papers in this small collection.
Related Archival Materials note
This small collection complements the Rusk material that is maintained as part of the archives of The Rockefeller Foundation. The Foundation archives contain a relatively brief officer's diary kept by Rusk, and correspondence by and to him. The most substantive correspondence appears in numerous grant administration (Record Group 1) and program and policy (Record Group 3) files. This documentation shows the Foundation's president in many respects functioning as a first among equals, often actively exchanging views with division officers and then making a final decision. Mr. Rusk's Secretary of State records are housed in the National Archives in Washington, D.C.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research ith select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Dean Rusk papers were donated to the RAC via correspondence from Virgina F. Rusk tp RAC Director Darwin H. Stapleton in 1995.
Public welfare; Philanthropy; Taxation -- Law and legislation -- United States; International relations -- United States -- 1950-1960.
- Subject Files, 1950-1969; 1
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged alphabetically and by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1 contains five folders of correspondence (1950-1969) between Rusk and various academic, political, and philanthropic leaders, including Henry Kissinger, Dean Acheson, Eleanor Roosevelt, Adlai Stevenson, Senator Ralph E. Flanders, and Raymond Fosdick. The correspondence covers such topics as meetings to discuss the defense of Europe, the implications of the Korean War, operation of the United Nations, foreign affairs, and Rusk's opinions on his colleagues' writings on foreign policy.
  Also present in Series 1 is correspondence (1958-1960) relating to the U.S. Senate Subcommittee on Policy, which was chaired by Senator Henry Jackson, to study the effectiveness of existing national security policy in regard to communism. Rusk's correspondence with Senator Jackson reveals Rusk's thoughts and advice on the study.
  - Clippings and Articles, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (A-D), 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (E-F), 1950-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (G-J), 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (K-R), 1952-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (S-Z), 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Name Lists, 1953, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Notes, 1952, 1958, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Souvenirs, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Trip to Indonesia, August-September 1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - United States Government - National Academy of Sciences - Academy of Public Affairs, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - United States Government - Senate Subcommittee on Policy, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - United States Government - Senate Subcommittee on Policy - Statements by Committee and by Senator Henry Jackson, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Published Articles, 1953-1962; 2
  This series is arranged chronologically by date of publication.
  Most of the articles in this series discuss U.S. foreign policy and diplomacy during the 1950's at the height of the Cold War.
  - International Organization, UN Charter (Possible Article), 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Statement Before Investigative Committee - 83rd Congress - Rockefeller Foundation (RF) and General Education Board (GEB), 1954 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Communication of Political Ideas" - Association of Princeton Graduate Alumni, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Parliamentary Diplomacy" - World Affairs Interpreter, Summer 1955 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "Building a Professional Staff" - New York University Institute on Federal Taxation, October 1955 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Hearings - Committee on Foreign Relations, Technical Assistant Programs, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "Tax Exemption and the Public Purse" - Junior Chamber of Commerce, January 25, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "Can We Break the Stalemate with Russia?" - Herald Tribune, March 16, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Harvard Law School Address, April 24, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "United States Readiness for War" - Industrial College of the Armed Forces, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "Neighborhood and Frontiers" - Arizona Business and Economic Review, May 1959 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - The University and World Affairs (The Ford Foundation), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "Common Interest and Marginal Hostility" - American College of Surgeons Bulletin, January-February 1960 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "The Past and the Future" - The Texas Quarterly, Spring 1960 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "The President" - Foreign Affairs, April 1960 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - "The United States and China" - (The Committee of One Million), 1961 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Current Biography, July 1961 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Replies to Dean Rusk Article, "The President", 1962 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Speeches, 1951-1961; 3
  This series is arranged chronologically by the date of the speech. The series also includes an index of speeches given between 1951 and 1960; the index is located at the beginning of the series in folder 32.
  Series 3, Speeches, which represents nearly three-quarters of the collection, contains copies of the speeches Rusk gave to various organizations and institutions from 1951 to 1961, together with notes and correspondence.
  Among the central themes of Rusk's speeches are foreign policy and the promotion of American democracy, particularly with regard to the Soviet Union, Korea, Japan, and the operation of the United Nations. Folder 36 contains a copy of the unofficial text of the Security Treaty between the U.S. and Japan (1952). In folder 88 there is correspondence from Harry S. Truman (1960), in which Truman responds to Rusk's recently published article "The President" in "Foreign Affairs" (1960).
  Other speeches concern the role of philanthropy, the importance of public and social welfare, and the contributions of The Rockefeller Foundation. Two folders in particular address this theme in a political context. Folders 53 and 54 contain material on the Reece Committee (1954) that was formed to investigate tax-exempt foundations, including The Rockefeller Foundation and the General Education Board, and to decide if legislation should be passed that would affect foundations. Folder 53 contains the combined statement of The Rockefeller Foundation and the General Education Board to the Reece Committee (1954). Present in folder 54 is the text of Rusk's remarks (1954) to the staff of The Rockefeller Foundation concerning the Reece Committee and Rusk's reactions to allegations that philanthropy supported something of a left-wing influence in American society.
  - Index, 1951-1960 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - China Institute in America, New York City, May 18, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Decision Making, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "Stalin on Stalinism", 1952 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Trip to Japan, January-February 1952 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Canadian Society of New York, March 7, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Aid Refugee Chinese Intellectuals, Inc., April 28, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Agnes Scott College Commencement, Atlanta, Georgia, June 2, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Southern Resource Development Foundation, September 18, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - English-Speaking Union, New York City, November 6, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Water Resources, 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - "Higher Education", 1953-1958 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Relations with United Soviet Socialist Republic (USSR), 1953 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - "Adventures in Science" - Tape Recording for CBS, February 7, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Conference on Higher Education, Chicago, Illinois, March 5, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Columbia University, Florina Lasker Memorial Lecture, March 18, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Howard University Law School, Washington, D.C., June 1, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - University of Pittsburgh Commencement, June 10, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Fifth Avenue Association, September 29, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Scarsdale, New York - Parent-Teachers Association, October 19, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Tulane University Convocation, New Orleans, Louisiana, October 28, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - United States Congress - Submission for Reece Committee, August 1954 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Reaction to Reece Committee, November-December 1954 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - United States Government - Senate Subcommittee on Technical Assistance, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - New York State Council for the Social Studies, February 11, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Vanderbilt University Commencement, June 5, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, June 22, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Occidental College, July 20, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Regrets, 1956-1960 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - American Assembly, Columbia University, New York City, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Junior Chamber of Commerce, Cincinnati, Ohio, January 25, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - United Negro College Presidents Convocation, Cleveland, Ohio, March 18, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Southern University Conference, Edgewater Park, Mississippi, April 13, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Smith College, Elizabeth Cutter Morrow Lecture, April 17, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - National Fund for Medical Education, April 23, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Southwestern, Memphis, Tennessee, June 5, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Army War College, Carlisle, Pennsylvania, September 14, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Association of Princeton Graduate Alumni, December 30, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Athenaeum, Summit, New Jersey, January 10, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Interchurch Council, March 28, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - National Academy of Sciences, April 23, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Scarsdale, New York Democratic Club, May 26, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Harvard Seminar - "The Role of the Secretary of State", October 28, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Virginia Women's Forum, November 7, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Dartmouth Great Issues Course, February 3-4, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Association of Johns Hopkins Alumni, April 11, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Harvard Law School Association, April 24, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - University of Texas-Austin Commencement, May 31, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Manufacturing Chemists' Association, November 25, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Brookings Institution, December 4, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Miami Beach Chamber of Commerce, December 10, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - University of Arizona-Tucson, March 6, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - American Association of University Women - Scarsdale, New York, April 23, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Industrial College of the Armed Forces, April 27, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - American College of Surgeons, September 28, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Scarsdale, New York Inter-Church Men's Club Dinner, February 15, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Elihu Root Lectures, March-August 1960 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Washington Mills Club, March 23, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Eastchester, New York - Parent-Teachers Association, March 24, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Asilomar, May 8, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Institute of International Education, May 10, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Industrial College of the Armed Forces, Washington, D.C., May 12, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - U. S. Army Commandant Armed Forces Staff College, June 29, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - National War College, August 31, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Chamber of Commerce of the United States, September 8-9, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - CBS Radio Program, September 12, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Foundations Group, September 20, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - U. S. Army War College, October 3, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - West Coast Trip, November 1-17, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Conference of The Associated Colleges at Claremont, California, November 9-10, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Associated Students of Mills College, November 15-16, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - West Point, December 1960 (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - Academy of Political Science, November 28, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 104)
- Dean Rusk photographs, 1066; 0.1 Cubic Feet
  Conditions Governing Access
  Photographs, slides, and other images are open for research.
  RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply.
  Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers.
  Photographs
  - Dean Rusk - Ceremonies (Box 56, Folder 690)